My name is Alain Reynaud. I've been working at Soundfull for four years and a half now.
I'm the lead character artist there so I was mostly working on the all the main
characters like from the main cast but also I was working on a lot of enemies,
boss, a small amount of NPCs but also alternative skins. So Expedition 33 is a
turn-based RPG with real-time elements like during the combats when you have to
parry, you have to dodge enemies attack, you also have to time your attacks to
make them more powerful. It's set in a French Belle Epoque you know like with a
lot of Art Deco themes and everything. So the story starts 67 years ago at the
city of Lumiere where in this world you have the big monolith at the center of
it and at the bottom of it there's a paint dress who every year paints a
number.
And everyone of that age with the with the age is the number written on the
monolith disappear. So we have an expedition every year who tries to stop
the paint dress from committing the gommage and to save the world. So you
John, Mael, Gustave and everyone on this expedition to stop the paint dress. I
worked a bit on the concept art but the the main concept artist and also our art
director is Nicolas Maxon-Franconc which is the
the art director for the project and we were really working closely together to
make the characters. Since we are a small studio it was easier you know to
have a lot of discussion about hey let's make it more that way let's make it more
this way and how we would do it is like Guillaume or Broche or game director would
give us the script about the character and give us a little description. Nicolas would make a
concept and then I will work with him to refine it. Yeah this was important from
the team for for everyone to have like this overall view of the project you
know. So everyone is on the same page and this helps brings more creativity to the
project. It's important to have a big vision for us of everything here. So a
lot of the inspiration comes from the Belle Epoque you know in France. So yeah we have
a big coach you know like those very classy suits for men and everything. So these were
drawing Nicolas made for us to have like a reference and also to make the city of Lumière
you know like have this really color like a lot of different colors for for everyone.
Here also like you can see the dress but also all the art deco pattern on everything which was really
for us like give this art deco vibe and to bring a lot of colors to to the city of Lumière. How I
will approach adjustment in art direction in Marvelous is because I will try to make
the best base possible in Marvelous because if I were to make something in Marvelous and
I would know that I would change 99% of it in ZBrush. Well there's no use to it.
So I would try to make like something as fitted as possible, for me, in Marvelous.
So that I would get the main shape, the main dynamics on
the fold and everything, so that it's perfect for me and would like show it to our art director
and only then I would export it and refine it in ZBrush. It was really important for us to
make the closing give as much information of the character as possible
like for example Ciel which is a character in our game has a very like
bright personalities and but she also had a hard life and we wanted to show it
in her clothing but we also did the same for everyone for example Lune who is a
more like she's more cold personality and everything she's following the rule
disciplined and so we wanted to show it on the characters too for example Ciel
she doesn't follow the rule as much as Lune she has like asymmetrical
clothing she also has a light thing but she also she she's a warrior so she has
these big pants and the knife so she can
move around with her small coat and it's kind of the opposite for Lune you know
like she has this much more symmetrical uniform like she has the the the coat
and everything which give her this look of like very following the rule and
everything we did this for all the characters like we needed to like if you
saw the character and her clothing you instantly understand
okay what type of personality she or he has so Maëlle she's a young girl
she's the youngest of the crew she didn't fit in Lumière and she wanted to
go to the expedition she wanted to explore the world and everything
and we wanted to showcase that in a uniform especially for fighting style
she has like a small sword that and she was she's very fast and very agile and
so we made her clothing with not a big coat but on the contrary like a very
tight pants high boots also like this really like class classy top with the
bright color and also like this small coat this give her this look of like okay
she's a fast and agile girl personally I have a special way to work with
Marvelous I don't tend to make files with
every clothing in one because I want to focus on only one part of the character
so for example this is the file for the pants where I would only have like the
the view of the the patterns and the 3d view and I would only focus on the pants
so like this was the pants that I work on after the Marvelous path and then I
would like work on the on the coat so this is how I would do it
I would just bring the important bikes as the avatar and then I would walk on
the coat to have the like big important shape for me and especially on the arm I
wanted to have like those diamond shapes here and also on the back also I wanted
to have like those those big crease I wanted to have a big shoulder here I
love this kind of shape and this is why I love marvelous is that it allows me to
me to work on the shape more precisely and yeah and I would freeze some parts
like for example I didn't want the sleeves to go on the forearm so yeah
okay let's just instead of like trying to make it tighter and everything I
would just freeze this part and I know it won't move you know also I can just
copy paste this and just send it to another one so I would know like okay so
the pants of I don't know CL or Lune is cool I want to put it on Verso for
example or I don't know I can just open the file of CL pants copy paste
everything put it on the other one for Verso then I would move things around
that it will match so this helped me create like a library of clothing for
all the characters
so yeah it's hard to recognize him but what I would like what I like to do is
like make a basic shape of the characters that I want so I would make
like a really simple shape in the in ZBrush to the overall proportion of the
characters and then I would import it into Marvelous and then it's just like
you just do pants like you would do except you move things around
to fit it and like for example like when I say earlier that don't be scared
to move away from from your reference like you wouldn't find reference of
pants like this on the internet especially that shape but what's really
important for me is the result here I don't care about this if this helped me
make something good here that's that's what important so that's why I have
those weird shape I would move things around you know like okay I want a
I want it, for example, I want it to have like big fold here, so I would give more closing
to that side here to help push it, have more of those big folds, you know.
This is what's important for me.
Like here, since it's more humanoid, I would make something that would be more close to
real life pattern, as you can see here.
And I can move like the shoulder to have those big folds.
I would freeze some parts, you know, to make it tighter.
I could use also the elastic things, but I prefer to have those kind of things with the
freezing because it gives me more liberties.
And so this was really important for me to have like those big shapes.
So I would like make, for example, this is the...
The pattern for this, and I would make it wider than the other one to give like all
those big wrinkles that I like.
That's the same for this.
When you compare the size of this to this, it's way bigger and that's what I liked about
it because it helped me have like those big folds that I find really cool looking.
And it's the same here.
And then everything is just falling in.
Yeah.
Really, really perfectly, and I would use seam taping to make it more sturdier and to
have a big shape that I like.
Yeah, so my experience with Marvelous Designer is like, it's super fun when you discover
it for the first time, then it's really hard to master it.
But once you do, it's really cool because you have this tool that makes you really good
looking, closing very fast, and really great result in a very short of time.
So once you get how it works, this helps save a lot of time.
And this is a really, really good tool for every artist, I think.
What I would recommend to all the other artists who wants to learn Marvelous is that just
move things around.
Don't be scared to be away from your reference.
Because the more you learn, the better.
Yeah.
Because the most important thing is the end result.
Expedition 3 has a big place in my heart, because it really changed me as a human being.
The next step for me is trying to be even better at Marvelous, because I know there's
a lot of tools that I don't know how to use.
I want to be a better sculptor, I want to make better texture and everything.
So this was my goal four years ago, and it's still my goal.
And I think it's going to be my goal my whole life.